Finding Aid for the Eugene E. Barnett Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Eugene E. Barnett Papers
1888-1967
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0033
.42 linear feet
Biography/History
Eugene Epperson Barnett was born in 1888 in Leesburg, Florida. He received a B.A. from Emory University in 1907; post-graduate study in the School of Religion at Vanderbilt University, 1907-1908; and received Honorary Degree of LL.D., from Emory University in 1944, and University of North Carolina in 1946.
He was the General Secretary of the National Council of YMCA’s from 1908-1910. He continued his work with the International Committee of the YMCA. From 1910-1936 he worked in China. While in China, he observed many religious and political changes including the downfall of Chiang Kai-Shek and the resurgence of Communism. After leaving China, he continued to work for the YMCA until his retirement in 1953. He traveled extensively before and after retirement. He died in 1970.
The autobiographical manuscript written by Eugene E. Barnett gives detailed information on his family background (the Barnett and Epperson Families), his boyhood, his college years with his involvement with the YMCA, the lives of his family both at home and abroad, and his many experiences. The memoir covers in great detail the following subjects:
Physical descriptions of Shanghai and Hangchow
YMCA work in Hangchow
Boxer Rebellion
Collapse of Ch’ing Dynasty
Economic Depression
Cultural Life in China
Anti-American Sentiment
World War I
Japanese Invasion of Manchuria
Siege of Shanghai by Japanese Forces
Marxism
Communism
USSR (Soviet Union)
Although intended to be a three-chapter autobiographical manuscript, the last chapter was not written.
Scope and Contents
This .21 linear feet collection contains correspondence, vita, book review, and an 304-page typescript autobiographical manuscript. The manuscript is divided into 20 sections and has been put in file folders by section number.
- Correspondence – Outgoing
  - to Woodrow W. Wasson, July 4, 1967
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - from Sherman P. Carter, December 6, 1966
- Book Review
  - Prophet of Plenty: The First Ninety Years of W. D. Weatherford by Wilma Dykeman, University of Tennessee Press, December 6, 1966; 1966
- Manuscript
  - As I Look Back: Recollections of Growing up in America’s Southland and of Twenty-Six years in Pre-Communist China, 1888-1936
    Section I Preview 1-6
    Section II Forebears 7-22
    Section III Boyhood 23-37
    Section IV College and University 38-49
    Section V Choosing and Starting My Life Work 50-64
    Section VI Taking Off 65-77
    Section VII Heaven Below 78-86
    Section VIII Preparing for Action 87-101
    Section IX Our First Term in Hangchow 102-121
    Section X To the U.S.A. and Back 122-136
    Section XI Hangchow “Mission Accomplished” 137-155
    Section XII Hangchow Postscript 156-169
    Section XIII Changing Gear—Shifting Winds 170-185
    Section XIV How to Spend a Furlough 186-199
    Section XV Into Heavy Weather 200-221
    Section XVI How Chinese Communism Looked To me during its Salad Years 222-240
    Section XVII More Stresses and Strains 241-261
    Section XVIII On the China Home Stretch (A) 262-278
    Section XIX On the China Home Stretch (B) 279-293
    Section XX On the China Home Stretch (C) 294-304
    Footnote 304
    Addendum to Closing Three Chapters [chapter not written] 305-346
- Vita
  - Dated January 18, 1960